<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Articles on Home</title><link>https://eamadio.github.io/post/</link><description>Recent content in Articles on Home</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2017 12:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://eamadio.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to set up this website using Hugo part 1</title><link>https://eamadio.github.io/post/set-hugo-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://eamadio.github.io/post/set-hugo-1/</guid><description>My career is shifting, and I&amp;rsquo;m steering it towards web development, mostly backend. Coming from digital electronics &amp;amp; embedded systems, I have a broad view on the digital ecosystem and I need a space where to show case my work and ideas. Having a github account is nice, but I wanted a place where I could publish articles online. It can be of any form like tutorial, blogs, reviews, editorials and much more.</description></item><item><title>How to set up this website using Hugo part2</title><link>https://eamadio.github.io/post/set-hugo-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://eamadio.github.io/post/set-hugo-2/</guid><description>In part 1 we explored how I created a website using Hugo, now we are going to create a github action to automatically deploy the site on github pages when we create a commit.
Set up of Git repositories I created 2 GitHub repositories for the project:
First Repository for the hugo project eamadio.github.io.hugo Second repository to host my blog as Github User page eamadio.github.io You can find on a lot of articles who are using 2 differents branches of the same repository (&amp;ldquo;main&amp;rdquo; for the project, &amp;ldquo;gh_pages&amp;rdquo; for the generated static files), however I prefere to have two distinct repositories, each one dealing with a different concern.</description></item></channel></rss>